Finding aid for the J. Paul Getty Museum, Getty Villa Construction Records, 1960, 1964, 1968-1986 and undated (bulk 1971-1974) IA10001
Institutional Records and Archives
Getty Villa construction records
1960,
1964,
1968-1986,
undated
(bulk 1971-1974)
Institutional Records and Archives
Fredericksen, Burton B.
Dinwiddie Construction Company
Bramlett, Norris (Cagle Norris)
J. Paul Getty Museum
Garrett, Stephen
Langdon and Wilson Architects
Getty, J. Paul (Jean Paul), 1892-1976
Wilson, Gillian, 1941-
IA10001
41.4 Linear Feet (30 boxes, 6 oversize boxes, 3 photo albums, 6 flat file drawers)
Correspondence, reports from the architects and builders, legal and financial documents, blueprints and models, photos, printed matter and oral histories, dating 1960, 1964, 1968-1986, undated (bulk 1971-1974) concern the design and construction of the J. Paul Getty Museum (Villa).
Related Archival Materials Note
The following materials are offered as possible sources of further information on the agencies and subjects covered by the records. The listing is not exhaustive.
Getty Research Institute Special Collections
Collection of Norman Neuerburg's documents relating to the construction of the J. Paul Getty Museum, 1970-1987 (call number 870517).
Acquisition Information
Assembled from the following acquisitions:1986.IA.08; 1986.IA.19; 1986.IA.36; 1987.IA.02; 1987.IA.03; 1987.IA.24; 2009.IA.28; and 2013.IA.35.
Restrictions on Access
The records described in accessions 1986.IA.19, 1986.IA.36, 1987.IA.02, 1987.IA.03, 1987.IA.24, and 2009.IA.28 are available for use by qualified researchers.
The records in accessions 1986.IA.08 and 2013.IA.35, subject to review for permanently closed information, are open to qualified researchers. Requests for access will be reviewed on a case-by-case basis.
The following records are permanently closed: records containing personal information, records that compromise security or operations, legal communications, legal work product, and records related to donors. The J. Paul Getty Trust reserves the right to restrict access to any records held by the Institutional Archives.
Scope and Content of Collection
Records consist of correspondence, memoranda, reports, legal and financial documents, drawings, blueline drawings, minutes, architectural models, photographic images, notes, printed matter, audiocassette tapes, lists, articles, clippings, indexes, contracts, drafts, amendments, permits, deeds, oral histories, and a bond, dating 1960, 1964, 1968-1986, undated (bulk 1971-1974), pertaining to the conceptual development and construction of the J. Paul Getty Museum (Villa). Norris Bramlett, Stephen Garrett, Langdon & Wilson, Norman Neuerburg, are especially prominent in the collection. Much of the correspondence consists of copies of outgoing letters and original incoming letters maintained by either Bramlett or Garrett; discussions concern Villa design, construction, maintenance, landscaping and irrigation, boundaries and easements, security, and various administrative and staff issues. Reports include material produced by Garrett for J. Paul Getty, site studies submitted to Langdon & Wilson, Architects, and "Specifications for Construction of the J. Paul Getty Museum" (and additional bulletins) produced by Langdon & Wilson. Legal documents include permits, permissions, and inspections required by the City of Los Angeles, a performance bond, guarantees and warranties, and contracts with the consultants and companies. Architects and consultants budgets record the budget estimates, invoices, and expenses of the architects and consultants who worked on the Villa construction project.
Dinwiddie Construction Co. records include minutes and supporting documentation summarize meetings held by Dinwiddie Construction Co. and attended by various contractors and consultants, job diaries filled out by the Dinwiddie site superintendent to document the ongoing construction, schedules, and budget, billing, and payroll files. An incomplete set of blueline prints and architectural drawings were created for the Villa construction project by Langdon & Wilson, the primary architects, and by Stephen Garrett, John S. Gregory Co, Emmet Wemple, Garth Benton, and David Wilkins. The drawings were used to describe, in technical detail, various aspect of the Villa building, from the overall site plan to cross-sectional views and to details of both mosaic floors and plumbing schematics.
Additional records include models representing the Decorative Arts Period Rooms of the Villa museum, photographs documenting the entire construction process, oral histories describing the development of the Villa, and a few printed materials.
Organization
The collection is organized into ten series:
Series I. Correspondence, 1968-1981
Series II. Reports, 1968-1974
Series III. Legal, 1968-1975
Series IV. Architect and consultant budgets, 1968-1976
Series V. Dinwiddie Construction Company records, 1970-1975
Series VI. Blueline prints and architectural drawings, 1964, 1968, 1970-1977, undated
Series VII. Models, 1972-1973, 1987, undated
Series VIII. Photographs, 1969-1974, 1976, undated
Series IX. Oral and written histories, 1972, 1980, 1986
Series X. Printed matter and notes, 1960, undated.
Administrative History
After considering various options for expanding his ranch house in Malibu California which had served as a private museum since 1954, J. Paul Getty decided in the fall of 1968 to build a new museum on the same property, in the form of a first-century Roman country house, based primarily on the plans of the ancient Villa dei Papiri just outside of Herculaneum. The archaeologist Norman Neuerburg, who had studied the ruins of Herculaneum and was an authority on Roman domestic architecture, was retained as a consultant for the project. The Santa Monica firm Langdon & Wilson was hired as architect, and Stephen Garrett, who had served as Getty's consultant in the remodeling of a Getty home in Posillipo, Italy, was retained as overseer of the construction. Landscape architect Emmet Wemple designed the gardens, Garth Benton worked on the murals, and Bruce Ptolomy worked on the fountains. The construction itself was done by Dinwiddie Construction Co., with various subcontractors. Construction began on December 21, 1970, and the new museum opened to the public on January 16, 1974. Despite the enthusiastic public response, mixed critical response questioned the decision to recreate an ancient building.
Upon the death of Mr. Getty and the subsequent establishment of the J. Paul Getty Trust, the Getty Villa became part of a larger vision. The Villa was redesigned by architects Machado and Silvetti Associates and reopened in 2006. While most of the Museum's collections are housed at the Getty Center in Los Angeles, the antiquities collection is still housed at the Villa. The Getty Villa serves a varied audience through the permanent collection, changing exhibitions, conservation, scholarship, research, and public programs in an intimate setting overlooking the Pacific Ocean. Public and scholarly programs at the Villa include lectures, seminars, conferences, workshops, symposia, film series, musical concerts, and theatrical performances in the Barbara and Lawrence Fleischman Outdoor Classical Theater.
Servitudes; Zoning; Clippings (information artifacts); Architecture -- Designs and plans; Nonprofit organizations -- Buildings; Oral histories (document genres); Contracts; Architectural records; Architecture -- Roman influences; Notes; Legal documents; Museums -- Security measures; Audiocassettes; Malibu (Calif.); Reports; Art museum architecture; Architecture -- Decision making; Building materials; Blueline prints; Building sites -- Planning; Reprographic copies; Memorandums; Lists; Bonds (legal records); Deeds; Building permits; Amendments (administrative records); Drawings (visual works); Financial records; Drafts (documents); Indexes (reference sources); Buildings -- Environmental engineering; Art -- Exhibition techniques; Photographs; Art museums -- Design and construction; Models (representations); Building designers; Minutes; Contractors' operations; Building -- Details; Correspondence; Building -- Equipment and supplies; Landscape construction; Building -- Estimates; Buildings -- Specifications; Frel, Jiří; Getty Villa (Malibu, Calif.); Neuerburg, Norman; J. Paul Getty Museum
- Correspondence, 1968-1981; Series I.; 1.45 Linear Feet (3.5 boxes)
  Organization
  These records are organized into two subseries:
  Series I.A. Chronological correspondence, 1968-1975
  Series I.B. Stephen Garrett correspondence, 1969-1981.
  Scope and Contents note
  Records comprise correspondence, memoranda, reports, notes, a few specifications, photographs, and oversize plats, dating from 1968 to 1975, pertaining to the conceptual development and construction of the J. Paul Getty Museum (Villa). Much of the correspondence consists of copies of outgoing letters and original incoming letters maintained by either Norris Bramlett or Stephen Garrett. The majority of the correspondence maintained by Bramlett passed between Getty and members of the Trust/Museum as they discussed the development and construction of the Villa, recording the evolution of planning from a proposed expansion of the existing ranch house museum wing to the construction of the Villa museum. Most of the correspondence maintained by Garrett consists of copies of outgoing letters and original incoming letters Garrett wrote, received, or was copied in on during the course of working for J. Paul Getty and with the staff of the Getty Trust and Museum on the Villa project. The materials contain discussions the Villa design, construction, maintenance, landscaping and irrigation, boundaries and easements, security, and various administrative and staff issues.
  - Chronological correspondence, 1968-1975; Series I.A.; 0.42 Linear Feet (1 box)
    Arrangement
    Files are listed in chronological order. The original order of the records, however, appears to have been in reverse chronological order and the documents within the files remain in reverse chronological order.
    Records comprise correspondence, memoranda, reports, and an oversize plan of Los Liones Canyon, dating from 1968 to 1975, pertaining to the conceptual development and construction of the J. Paul Getty Museum (Villa). Much of the correspondence consists of copies of outgoing letters and original incoming letters maintained by Norris Bramlett. The majority of the correspondence passed between Getty and members of the Trust/Museum as they discussed the development and construction of the Villa. Memoranda were often written to the file to record conversations with and instructions from Getty. The documents record the evolution of planning from discussion of a simple expansion of the existing ranch house museum wing to the construction of what became the Villa museum.
    Specific subjects under discussion include the planned design of the Villa and issues such as security and security systems, gallery arrangement and the display of objects, the flow of visitors, environmental controls, potential maintenance issues, decoration, lighting, staff work space, parking, and access to storage areas. The files also include discussions of building orientation, the development and approval of plans and blueprints, land ownership, zoning and permits, landscaping, construction materials, cost estimates, the sale of Getty Oil stock to fund the construction, preparations for the opening, instructions from Getty on the creation of a museum art catalog and, occasionally, instructions from Getty on the purchase of art.
    Letters and memos were predominantly written by Norris Bramlett, Stephen Garrett, J. Paul Getty, Burton Fredericksen, Norman Neuerburg, and Langdon & Wilson (architects). On infrequent occasions correspondence is generated by Janet Fox, Carole Tier, Frank Whitworth, and various consultants.
    Some files in this subseries are closely related to the next subseries. Each set of files contains unique documents, but some of the correspondence is duplicated. Sometimes an incoming letter or cc. from, for example, Stephen Garrett maintained in this subseries is found as a copy of an outgoing letter in the next subseries, likewise a copy of an outgoing letter to Garrett in these files seems to have its original in the next subseries. The same is true for some of the correspondence between Garrett and other members of the Trust and Museum as well as with Langdon & Wilson.
    - April-December 1968 (Box 1986.IA.08-01, Folder 1)
    - January-July 1969
      - Papers (Box 1986.IA.08-01, Folder 2)
    - August-December 1969 (Box 1986.IA.08-01, Folder 3)
      General note
      [File also contains a formal report (Report #1) from Stephen Garrett to J. Paul Getty on the Museum construction following Garrett's exploratory trip to Los Angeles in July 1969.]
    - January-July 1970 (Box 1986.IA.08-01, Folder 4)
      (Correspondence in March 1970 first mentions the Villa dei Papiri)
    - August 1970 (Box 1986.IA.08-01, Folder 5)
    - September-October 1970 (Box 1986.IA.08-01, Folder 6)
    - November-December 1970 (Box 1986.IA.08-01, Folder 7)
    - January-November 1971 (Box 1986.IA.08-01, Folder 8)
    - December 1971-February 1972 (Box 1986.IA.08-01, Folder 9)
    - March-October 1972 (Box 1986.IA.08-01, Folder 10)
    - November 1972-December 1973 (Box 1986.IA.08-01, Folder 11)
    - January-June 1975 (Box 1986.IA.08-01, Folder 12)
  - Stephen Garrett correspondence, 1969-1981; Series I.B.; 1.03 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
    Records are arranged either by correspondent or by subject matter. Some of the letters that were less well organized were refiled, and in some cases subject file titles were invented to describe folder contents. Within folders, records are in reverse chronological order.
    The records consist of correspondence, memoranda, notes, a few specifications, photographs, and an oversize plat, dating from 1969 to 1981 and maintained by Stephen Garrett, that pertain to the conceptual development and construction of the J. Paul Getty Museum (Villa). Much of the correspondence consists of copies of outgoing letters and original incoming letters Garrett wrote, received, or was copied in on during the course of working for J. Paul Getty and with the staff of the Getty Trust and Museum on the Villa construction project. The majority of the records were created while Garrett was in Getty's employ but still lived and worked in London, prior to his move to Southern California to work for the Museum as Deputy Director in July 1973.
    The materials cover various aspects and details of the Villa planning and design, construction, maintenance, landscaping and irrigation, establishment of boundaries and easements, security, and various administrative and staff issues. Some documents are annotated.
    Some files in this subseries are closely related to the previous subseries. Each set of files contains unique documents, but some of the correspondence is duplicated. Sometimes an incoming letter from, for example, Norris Bramlett maintained in this subseries is found as a copy of an outgoing letter in the previous subseries, likewise a copy of an outgoing letter to Bramlett, or a member of his staff, in these files seems to have its original in the previous subseries. The same is true for some of the correspondence with other members of the Trust and Museum as well as with Langdon & Wilson. Additionally, two of the files, one concerning Langdon & Wilson and one concerning Norman Neuerburg appear to have been maintained by Norris Bramlett, though Stephen Garrett appears prominently in the documents.
    - Benton, Garth, 1971-1973 (Box 1986.IA.08-02, Folder 1)
    - Bramlett, Norris, 1969-1972; (2 files) (Box 1986.IA.08-02, Folder 2-3)
    - Dinwiddie Construction Company:
      - 1971-1972, (2 files) (Box 1986.IA.08-02, Folder 4-5)
        [Records are generally in reverse chronological order by correspondent (Bill Gatewood (site supervisor) or Ted Smith) within the file.]
      - Bronze room (air conditioning issue), 1979-1981 (Box 2009.IA.28-1)
    - Fredericksen, Burton, 1970-1973 (Box 1986.IA.08-02, Folder 6)
    - Fredericksen, Burton and Wilson, Gillian, 1972-1973 (Box 1986.IA.08-02, Folder 7)
    - Frel, Jiri, 1973 (Box 1986.IA.08-02, Folder 8)
    - Getty, J. Paul, 1969-1973 (Box 1986.IA.08-02, Folder 9)
    - Langdon and Wilson, 1970-1973; (4 files) (Box 1986.IA.08-02, Folder 10-13)
      [This folder seems to be Norris Bramlett's file on Langdon and Wilson, Stephen Garrett figures prominently.]
    - Neuerburg, Norman, 1970-1974; (5 files) (Box 1986.IA.08-03, Folder 1-5)
      [Includes brief, handwritten resume of Neuerburg]
      [Folder 5 seems to be Norris Bramlett's file on Norman Neuerburg, Stephen Garrett figures prominently.]
    - Ptolemy, Bruce (fountain designer), 1972 (Box 1986.IA.08-03, Folder 6)
    - Wemple, Emmet (landscape architect):
      - 1971-1973 (Box 1986.IA.08-03, Folder 7)
      - 1973-1976 (Box 2009.IA.28-1)
    - BBC film, 1972 (Box 1986.IA.08-03, Folder 8)
    - Cracks in Peristyle Wall, 1973 (Box 1986.IA.08-03, Folder 9)
    - Early discussions, 1969-1970 (Box 1986.IA.08-03, Folder 10)
    - Excavations (Herculaneum), 1971 (Box 1986.IA.08-03, Folder 11)
    - Fire suppression, 1972 (Box 1986.IA.08-03, Folder 12)
    - Gatehouse, 1973 (Box 1986.IA.08-03, Folder 13)
    - Graphics consultant, 1972-1973 (Box 1986.IA.08-03, Folder 14)
    - Insurance, 1973 (Box 1986.IA.08-03, Folder 15)
    - Los Liones Canyon, Sunset Mesa exit easements, 1972-1973
      - Papers, 1972-1973 (Box 1986.IA.08-03, Folder 16)
      - Oversize, 1972-1973 (Flatfile 1986.IA.08-37)
    - Marbles, 1972-1973 (Box 1986.IA.08-03, Folder 17)
    - Mechanical systems, 1970-1971; 1973 (Box 1986.IA.08-03, Folder 18)
    - Moulder Brothers, 1974 (Box 1986.IA.08-03, Folder 19)
    - Pool Expenses (Bruce Ptolemy), 1971-1973 (Box 1986.IA.08-03, Folder 20)
    - Ranch House security, 1972 (Box 1986.IA.08-03, Folder 21)
    - Replica furniture, 1972-1973 (Box 1986.IA.08-03, Folder 22)
      (Portions of the correspondence are in Italian.)
    - Replica statuary, 1972-1973 (Box 1986.IA.08-03, Folder 23)
    - Restoration (John Brealey), 1971 (Box 1986.IA.08-03, Folder 24)
    - Security, 1971-1973 (Box 1986.IA.08-03, Folder 25)
- Reports, 1968-1974; Series II.; 2.1 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
  These records are organized into three subseries:
  Series II.A. Site studies, 1970, 1972-1974
  Series II.B. Reports from Stephen Garrett, 1968-1973
  Series II.C. Reports from architects and consultants, 1970-1974.
  The series includes reports, correspondence, memoranda, lists, articles, clippings, notes, and an index, dating 1968-1974, produced by the consultants, architects, and artisans who worked on the construction of the J. Paul Getty Museum (Villa). Site studies were submitted to Langdon & Wilson, Architects, regarding J. Paul Getty Museum (Villa) foundations and geologic conditions. Stephen Garret's reports include copies of 60 numbered reports created by him for J. Paul Getty. The reports detail specifics of the Villa planning and construction process which Getty, who was living in England at the time, either needed to be informed of or needed to make a decision about. Langdon & Wilson produced "Specifications for Construction of the J. Paul Getty Museum" in December 1970, and produced thereafter a series of Bulletins as amendments or supplements to the original document. Norman Neuerburg, Langdon & Wilson, and various contractors are represented in a few miscellaneous reports.
  - Site studies, 1970; 1972-1974; Series II.A.; 0.17 Linear Feet
    The Crandall reports precede the Brown reports.
    [Plastic spiral binders and covers have been removed - box contents are a little loose now - may need a spacer; the Geologic Investigation reports are on poor quality paper and should be photocopied]
    Records comprise reports and correspondence, dating 1970, 1972-1974, submitted to Langdon & Wilson, Architects, regarding J. Paul Getty Museum (Villa) foundations and geologic conditions. The foundation inspections were prepared by LeRoy Crandall and Associates in collaboration with Edward G. Genter, Jr. and Brandow & Johnston Associates, Structural Engineers. The geologic investigations were performed by Glenn A. Brown and Associates.
    - Report of Foundation Investigation, Proposed Gate Entrance Structure, 1972-1973; [2 copies] (Box 1986.IA.08-04, Folder 1)
    - Report of Foundation Investigation, Proposed Building, 1970; [2 copies] (Box 1986.IA.08-04, Folder 2)
    - Inspection and Testing of Compacted Fill, and Inspection of Foundation Excavations Museum and Parking Structure, 1974
      - Papers, 1974 (Box 1986.IA.08-04, Folder 3)
      - Oversize, 1974 (Flatfile 1986.IA.08-37)
    - Geologic Investigation, Entry and Guard House, 1973; [2 copies] (Box 1986.IA.08-04, Folder 4)
  - Reports from Stephen Garrett, 1968-1973; Series II.B.; 1.25 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
    The records are arranged chronologically. At least two copies of most reports have been preserved.
    Records include reports, correspondence, memoranda, lists, notes, and an index, dating 1968-1973, maintained in the offices of Norris Bramlett. Stephen Garret prepared 60 numbered reports for J. Paul Getty detailing specifics of the Villa planning and construction process which Getty, who was living in England at the time, either needed to be informed of or needed to make a decision about. Copies of these reports were sent to the Getty Trust in Los Angeles. The reports are often structured in sections describing the work that had been accomplished, offering recommendations, and proposing questions to be answered by Getty. A number of the reports simply summarize discussions held with and decisions made by Getty. Some reports are accounts of meetings with people involved in the Villa project, others seem to include subjects and points of interest which Garrett felt were of interest to Getty, such as a translation of a 19th century text about the Villa dei Papiri. In between the numbered reports, there are shorter memos, correspondence, and notes, typically summarizing discussions and decisions reached in meetings held to review issues raised in the reports.
    - Index/Listing of reports by Stephen Garrett, 1970; undated (Box 1986.IA.08-04, Folder 5)
    - [Memoranda entitled] "Notes on proposed addition to existing museum" and "Comments on proposed design,", September 12, 1968; November 13, 1968 (Box 1986.IA.08-04, Folder 6)
    - Report #1, August 5, 1969 (Box 1986.IA.08-04, Folder 7)
      [The file also includes a memorandum entitled "Decisions made by Mr. Getty...," September 8, 1969; with attached correspondence from Stephen Garrett to Bob Langdon and Norris Bramlett ( September 9, 1970 ); and correspondence from Burton Fredericksen to Norris Bramlett, re. Report #1, September 24, 1969 ]
    - Report #1, August 5, 1969 (Box 1986.IA.08-04, Folder 8)
      [Pages of the first copy are in need of preservation photocopying in the near future]
    - Report #2, December 10, 1969 (Box 1986.IA.08-04, Folder 9)
      [File also includes "Summary of Decisions made by Mr. Getty...," January 9, 1970 ]
    - Report #3, January 6, 1970 (Box 1986.IA.08-04, Folder 10)
      [Contains the first mention of the Villa dei Papiri.] [The file also contains two memos, dating March 20, 1970, "Background information relating to decisions made by Mr. Getty concerning the design of the museum" and "Summary of decisions made by Mr. Getty concerning the design of the museum."]
    - Report #4, January 9, 1970 (Box 1986.IA.08-04, Folder 11)